Inventory of the Irving C. Root papers, 1911-1972
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Irving C. Root papers
1911-1972
Root, Irving C.
05972
6.58 cubic ft. (14 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Irving C. Root was an architect, city planner, chief engineer/planning director, and superintendent of the National Capital Parks in Washington D.C. The collection contains materials regarding his professional career and the projects he helped to develop.
Biography of Irving C. Root
Irving C. Root (1891-1973) was an architect during the mid-20th century. He began his career as a city planner in Cambridge, Massachusetts (1916-1920) and Flint, Michigan (1920-1922). From 1922-1927 he pursued his own private practice as a planning consultant before becoming the Chief Engineer and Planning Director of the Maryland-National Capital Park and Planning Commission. In 1940 Root was appointed Superintendent of the National Capital Parks in Washington D.C. He held this post until 1953 when he returned to private practice as a planning consultant.
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials relating to Irving C. Root's involvement in city and national park planning including extensive subject files containing maps, architectural drawings, correspondence, publications, newspaper clippings, and articles and reports concerning projects for zoning, park systems, city planning, and the Maryland-National Capital Park and Planning Commission. The collection also contains files concerning his professional career and private practice. These files include correspondence, contracts, project prospects, newspaper clippings, articles and reports written by Root, and research files about zoning, park systems, and city planning.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Irving C. Root at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
This material was received from the estate of Irving C. Root and his son, Robert W. Root, in June 1975.
Access Terms
Maryland-National Capital Park and Planning Commission; City planning--United States; National parks and reserves--Washington (D.C.); National parks and reserves--Planning; Regional planning--United States; Landscape architecture; Michigan; Alexandria (Va.); Maryland; Potomac River; United States--History--20th century; Maps; Architectural drawings (visual works); Blueprints
Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences; Architecture; City Planning; National Parks
Container List
- Series I. Subject files
  This series contains correspondence, reports, legislation, articles, clippings, ordinances, maps, blueprints and architectural drawings, pamphlets, brochures, publications, notes, and photographs relating to specific projects and subjects that Root worked on during his professional career.
  - American Society of Planning Officials, 1962-1970 (Box 1)
  - Architectural control, 1928-1951 (Box 1)
  - Automobile parking, 1928-1955 (Box 1)
  - Bridge planning, 1921-1929 (Box 1)
  - Building code, 1949-1952 (Box 1)
  - Building lines, 1931-1935 (Box 1)
  - California - Folsom, 1952 (Box 1)
  - California - Sacramento-Folsom, 1952-1955 (Box 1)
  - Cape Cod, National Park Service, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Causeway Memorial Park, Muskegon, Michigan, 1925-1943 (Box 1)
  - Commercial - Industrial, 1923-1950 (Box 2)
  - Drafting, 1917-1964 (Box 2)
  - Government Services, Inc., 1964-1970 (Box 2)
  - Guam, 1948-1952 (Box 2-3, and 14)
  - Highway planning, 1920-1955 (Box 4)
  - Highway protect, 1930-1953 (Box 4)
  - Horticulture, 1926-1953 (Box 4)
  - Housing, 1931-1940 (Box 4)
  - Insects, 1911-1940 (Box 4)
  - Landscape, 1923-1935 (Box 4)
  - Maryland - Caroline County, 1963-1964 (Box 4)
  - Maryland - Centreville, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Maryland - Charles County, 1959-1968 (Box 4-5)
  - Maryland - Denton, 1961 (Box 5)
  - Maryland - Montgomery County, 1954-1956 (Box 5)
  - Maryland National Capitol Park and Planning Commission, 1927-1967 (Box 5)
  - Maryland state roads, 1952-1962 (Box 6)
  - Maryland - Talbot County, 1951-1967 (Box 6)
  - Michigan - Flint, 1920-1924 (Box 6 and 14)
  - Michigan - Miscellaneous, 1920-1971 (Box 6 and 14)
  - National Park Service, 1944-1968 (Box 7)
  - Nevada - Boulder City, 1944-1953 (Box 7)
  - Playgrounds, 1934-1954 (Box 7)
  - Railroads-Transportation, 1920-1925 (Box 7)
  - Regional planning, 1937 (Box 7)
  - Subdivision of land, 1924-1941 (Box 7)
  - Tennessee - Gatlinburg, 1946-1955 (Box 7)
  - Virgin Islands, 1955-1958 (Box 7)
  - Virginia - Alexandria, 1932 (Box 7)
  - Washington area, 1920-1960 (Box 8)
- Series II. Professional files
  This series contains article and report drafts, contracts, city planning publicity and reports, correspondence, legislation, and newspaper clippings regarding Root's professional life.
  - Article and report drafts, 1927-1953 (Box 8)
  - City planning promotion and publicity, 1913-1949 (Box 8)
  - City planning reports, 1920-1969 (Box 8-9)
  - Contracts, 1923-1962 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence:
    - Appointments, 1932-1952 (Box 9)
    - Commendatory, 1915-1968 (Box 9)
    - Letters of congratulations for appointment to Superintendent of National Capital Parks, 1940 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1927-1972 (Box 9)
  - Legislation and legal documents, 1928-1952 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1920-1964 (Box 9)
  - Prospects, 1950-1968 (Box 10)
  - Reports, 1937-1955 (Box 10)
  - Zoning, 1923-1960 (Box 10-11)
- Series III. Photographs
  This series contains photographs regarding Root's projects and professional career.
  - Carter Barron Amphitheatre - Rock Creek Park, Washington D.C., July 1950 (Box 11)
  - Chesapeake and Ohio Canal - Potomac River, 1942-1945 (Box 11)
  - Krug, Julius Albert - United States Secretary of the Interior, 1946-1949 (Box 11)
  - Maryland, 1936-1951 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1919-1946 (Box 11)
  - Monuments and markers, 1920-1950 (Box 11)
  - People, 1916-1950 (Box 11)
  - Potomac River, undated (Box 11)
  - Root, Irving C., 1945-1957 (Box 11)
  - Virginia, 1920-1950 (Box 11)
- Series IV. Maps
  This series contains subdivision maps, zoning and planning city maps, and architectural drawings regarding Root's projects as a city planner, private consultant, and chief engineer and superintendent for the National Capital Parks.
  - Maryland:
    - Charles County, undated (Box 12, Map Roll B)
    - Montgomery County, 1950 (Box 12, Map Roll B)
    - Gaithersburg, 1933 (Box 12, Map Roll A)
    - Rockville, undated (Box 12, Map Roll A)
  - Massachusetts: Concord, 1916 (Box 12, Map Roll A)
  - Michigan:
    - Flint, 1920-1924 (Box 11-12, Map Roll A and D)
    - Midland, 1920-1924 (Box 11-12, Map Roll A, B, and D)
    - Michigan Cities, Saint Joseph and Benton Harbor, 1925 (Box 12, Map Roll A, B)
    - Muskegon, undated (Box 12, Map Roll A, B)
    - Owosso, undated (Box 12, Map Roll B)
    - Saginaw, undated (Box 11-12, Map Roll A)
  - Missouri: Kansas City, 1917 (Box 12, Map Roll A)
  - Mount Vernon Memorial Highway, 1930 (Box 13, Map Roll C)
  - Nevada: Boulder City, 1951 (Box 12, Map Roll A)
  - Virginia: Alexandria, 1920-1927 (Box 11-13, Map Roll B, C, and D)
  - Washington D.C., 1918 (Box 11)